A Guide to the Film collection FA466
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA), 4; All of the CIAA films are available on DVD, except where noted.
  - Mexico Builds a Democracy, Sound, Color, 19 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1298, Box 2, Dvd AV 1298, Reel III 40 F 50)
    Education programs for the Tarascan Indians; presented by Contemporary Films.
  - Mexico City, Sound, Color, 11 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel III 40 F 25, Reel AV 1511)
    Tour of the city, narrated by Orson Welles; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department and Mitla Films
  - Montevideo Family, Sound, Black & white, 16 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 36, Reel AV 1299, Box 2, Dvd AV 1299)
    A day in the life of a typical middle class family; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
  - Our Neighbors Down the Road, Sound, Color, 42 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 60, Reel AV 1300, Box 2, Dvd AV 1300)
    Scenic tour along the Pan-American Highway, through Venezuela, Argentina, and Brazil; produced by Herbert Lanks/Pan-American Highway Confederation
  - La Paz, Sound, Black & white, 16 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 41, Reel AV 1294, Box 2, Dvd AV 1294)
    Footage of Indian market, folk dances, local architecture and construction; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
  - Peru's Coastal Region, Sound, Color, 11 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 7, Box 2, Dvd AV 1301, Reel AV 1301)
    Travelogue discussing agriculture, geography, architecture and society, Incan culture and related archaeological projects; narrated by Wendell C. Bennett.
  - Picturesque Patzcuaro, Sound, Color, 11 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 26, Box 2, Dvd AV 1302, Reel AV 1302)
    Narrated by Tyrone Power, produced by the Mexican Tourism Department
  - Que es Enfermedad (What is Disease?), 1945; Sound, Color, 11 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 22, Box 2, Dvd AV 1303, Reel AV 1303)
    Animated feature from Walt Disney Studios, part of the "Health for the Americas" series.
  - Ramon Esta Enfermo (Ramon Is Ill), Sound, Color, 11 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F11, Reel AV 1304, Box 2, Dvd AV 1304)
    Animated feature from Walt Disney Studios, part of the "Reading for the Americas" series (# 4).
  - La Riqueza de Los Andes (The Wealth of the Andes), Sound, Black & white, 28 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1305, Reel III 40 F 28, Reel AV 1305)
    History of Peru with a tour of Lima; footage of railroads, mines, hydroelectric plants; copper and lead smelting
  - The Road to Cuernavaca, Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1306, Reel III 40 F 23, Reel AV 1306)
    Travelogue produced by the Mexican Tourist Department: vacation resorts in Cuernavaca, Tasco, Acapulco; footage of murals by Diego Rivera; narrated by Tyrone Powers.
  - Roads South, Sound, Black & white, 18 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1307, Reel III 40 F 29, Reel AV 1307)
    Transportation in South America; geographic obstacles; Pan American highway; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
  - Saneamiento del Ambiente (Environmental Sanitation), 1945; Sound, Color, 8 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1308, Box 2, Dvd AV 1308, Reel III 40 F 19)
    Animated feature about a growing community and its sanitation needs: water supply, waste management, etc.; presented by Walt Disney Studios, as part of the "Health in the Americas" series.
  - Sao Paulo, Sound, Black & white, 15 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1309, Reel AV 1309, Reel III 40 F 52)
    Overview of Sao Paulo history, growth, industries, and standards of living; presented by the Office of Strategic Services.
    Three copies of access DVD.
  - Schools to the South, Sound, Black & white, 13 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1310, Reel AV 1310, Reel III 40 F 37)
    Education in Latin America; presented by Julien Bryan Productions
  - La Semilla de Oro (The Golden Grain), 1942; Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1311, Reel AV 1311, Reel III 40 F 2)
    Animated feature about the history and development of corn, the importance and usage of corn in the Mexican diet, and an introduction to related technology and science; presented by Walt Disney Studios
  - South Chile, Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1312, Box 2, Dvd AV 1312, Reel III 40 F 38)
    Visit to Indian reservation, the Straits of Magellan, resorts, sheep ranches; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
  - South of the Border With Disney, 1942; Sound, Color, 33 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1313, Box 2, Dvd AV 1313, Reel III 40 F 58)
    Tour with Walt Disney, wife, and staff through South American countries to promote good will and collect material for films; scenes of Rio de Janeiro, Montevideo, Buenos Aires, Argentina, Mendoza, Chile, La Paz, Lake Titicaca, Guatemala, and Mexico City; presented by Walt Disney Studios.
  - Southern Brazil, Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 53, Reel AV 1314, Box 2, Dvd AV 1314)
    Progress in Brazil from an agricultural to an industrial nation; produced by the Office of Strategic Services.
  - Tehauntepec, Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 1, Reel AV 1315, Box 2, Dvd AV 1315)
    City scenery: women at the marketplace, costume and jewelry descriptions, weddings and festivals; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department, narrated by Linda Darnell.
  - A Town in Old Mexico, Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 24, Reel AV 1316, Box 2, Dvd AV 1316)
    Visit to Puebla Fortin de las Flores, Orizaba; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department; narrated by Orson Welles.
  - La Tuberculosis, 1944; Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 17, Box 2, Dvd AV 1317, Reel AV 1317)
    Animated feature on the cause and treatment of Tuberculosis; produced by Walt Disney Studios.
  - Uncinariasis (Hookworm), 1945; Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 21, Box 2, Dvd AV 1318, Reel AV 1318)
    Animated feature on hookworm: how it attacks, spreads, and develops, and how to prevent it. Produced by Walt Disney Studios
  - Uruguay, Sound, Black & white, 18 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 35, Box 2, Dvd AV 1319, Reel AV 1319)
    Standards of living; explanation of government; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
  - Venezuela Moves Ahead, Sound, Color, 35 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 45, Reel AV 1505)
    Overview of Venezuela's history, geography, agriculture, culture, transportation, economy, education; presented by Julien Bryan Productions
  - Vera Cruz, Sound, Color, 18 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel III 40 F 45, Reel AV 1507)
    Urban and rural life of the region: dances, costumes, jewelry, other activities; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department; narrated by Joseph Cotton.
  - Yucatan: The Old Land of the Mayas, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel III 40 F 51, Reel AV 1508)
    History of Merida and its industry; Mayan, Itza and Chichen temples; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department; narrated by Charles Bickford (English version).
  - Water: Friend or Enemy?, 1942; Sound, Color, 9 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1320, Reel III 40 F 3, Reel AV 1320)
    Animated feature about the construction of wells to secure safe drinking water; presented by Walt Disney Studios.
  - The Winged Scourge, 1943; Sound, Color, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1321, Reel AV 1321, Reel III 40 F 6)
    Animated feature about protection against the anopheles mosquito with the Seven Dwarfs; presented by Walt Disney Studios
  - Wings Over Brazil, Sound, Black & white, 15 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1322, Reel AV 1322, Reel III 40 F 54)
    From the Office of Strategic Services, a documentary about Brazilian aviation pioneers in the Air Academy. Includes footage from a naval airbase during wartime.
  - Young Uruguay, Sound, Black & white, 17 minutes. Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1323, Reel AV 1323, Reel III 40 F 32)
    Schools, education and recreation; presented by Julien Bryan Productions
    Four copies of access DVD.
- Harold P. Fabian, 5; All of the footage has been compiled onto one DVD. These silent films each run about 2-5 minutes, and contain a mix of color and black and white stock.
  Arranged by accession.
  A group of eighteen home movies/travelogues from Harold P. Fabian. Shots of Yellowstone National Park, Jackson Hole, Cascade Canyon, Moose Church, and a rodeo.
  - Yellowstone, 1938; Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1326, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 1)
    Train arriving at Yellowstone; Morning Glory pool; geysers erupting; Kesler Cascade; black bear in forest; children playing
  - Wilson Rodeo, 1942; Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1327, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 10)
    Horseback riding with family; footage of rodeo
  - Summer 1939, Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1328, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 11, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343)
    Picnic with family; visiting the farm
  - East 1940, Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1329, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 12, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343)
    Fishing; crowds on street in formal attired; boarding United Airlines Mainliner; shots from air flying to Chicago.
  - New York October 1938, 1938 October; Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1330, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 13)
    Driving through Jackson Hole; Caribou National Forest; some very dark footage of cars.
  - Jackson Hole, July 1938, 1938 July; Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 14, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1331)
    Log cabins; views of mountains; visiting Elk Ranch
  - Summer 1942, 1942 Summer; Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 15, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1332)
    Farm equipment; boat ride on lake; mountain views; horseback riding.
  - Jackson Hole, 1938; Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 16, Reel AV 1333, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343)
    JY Ranch; horseback riding; making hay bales at farm
  - Boat Trip 1940, Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 17, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1334)
    Boat ride; horseback riding with family
  - Fabian, 1940; Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 18, Reel AV 1335, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343)
    Cascade Canyon: mountain views; fishing; horseback riding with family
  - Game in Yellowstone, 1939; Available on DVD. (Reel IV 3A7 Fa 2, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1336)
    Views of mountains and water; deer in forest
  - Moose Church, 1938; Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 3, Reel AV 1337)
    Chapel of the Transfiguration in Jackson Hole, Wyoming; horseback riding with family; views of mountains
  - June 1940, 1940 June; Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 4, Reel AV 1338)
    Family scenes at cabin; horseback riding with family
  - Cascade Canyon, 1940; Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1339, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 5)
    Fishing on lake; moose in the forest; panorama views from cabin.
  - Jackson Hole Summer 1939, 1939 Summer; Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1340, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 6)
    Fishing on lake; views of forest, geese, mountains
  - Geese on Phelps Lake, 1938; Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1341, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 7)
    Horseback riding with family; train arriving; children playing at lake.
  - Jackson Hole 1938, Available on DVD. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel AV 1342, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 8)
    Idaho Falls airport
  - Jackson Hole 1939, Available on DVD. (Reel AV 1343, Box 2, Dvd AV 1326-1343, Reel IV 3A7 Fa 9)
    Windmill; driving on highway; very dark footage of some nighttime gathering
- Ford Foundation, 6; Except where noted, the Ford Foundation films are only available on the original film format
  Alphabetical
  The films included in the collection are the products of various grants and internal initiatives, dating from the early 1950s.
  The Ford Foundation is a nonprofit grant-making organization with an extensive history of international leadership in economic development, human rights and microfinance, as well as major U.S. causes, including the environment, civil rights, legal aid, and women's rights, and such domestic challenges as urban development and reproductive health.
  - 4 Women Artists, 1977; Sound, Color, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1904)
    A documentary about traditional arts and storytelling in southern US communities, with interviews and footage of Eudora Welty, Pecolia Warner, and others. Directed by Bill Ferris. Funded by the Rockefeller Foundation, National Endowment for the Humanities, Mississippi Arts Commission, and the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1977, Center for Southern Folklore.
  - Abstraction, Sound, Color, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 1957, Reel AV 2004)
    Short film presented by the American Federation of Arts about the physics and characteristics of abstraction. Distorting physical items from science, nature, and intangible items in math and art can all be understood as abstraction. Abstract concepts in design, art, and language are shown. An ACI Release.
  - All About Life, Sound, Color, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 1780)
    Episode of TV series from unknown network hosted by Dr. Ron Pion. Features a pregnant woman and a panel of children who are queried about pregnancy and childbirth. Produced by Jeff Shiffman, a King Community Services Program.
  - Alternative Sentencing, Sound, Color, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 1902)
    Overcrowded prisons and outdated systems in Georgia required the state to explore nontraditional sentencing structures - their successes are documented in this short film. At the threat of federal involvement, the state designed new alternatives to prison time. The film shows several tiers of options for nonviolent criminals, and discusses the challenges and accomplishments of the programs. Funded by the Ford Foundation and the JFK School of Government at Harvard. Produced by David Jordan, copyright 1988 by GDC.
  - Aptitude Testing, Sound, Black & white, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 1847)
    Showcase of education and training opportunities for young people in Nigeria. A four-year study by the American Institute for Research and the US Agency for International Development produced an aptitude test, which was incorporated into school and professional systems throughout Nigeria. Details of the test and its outcomes are presented. This film is presented by the Ford Foundation in cooperation with the public authorities of Nigeria.
  - Are You Listening: Household Technicians, Sound, Color, 29 minutes. (Reel AV 1900)
    An episode of the series "Are You Listening?" featuring women who work as domestic employees and maids. Issues of respect, education, and benefits are discussed from the point of view of the household technician.
  - Art of Seeing, Sound, Color, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 1898)
    Short film presented by the American Federation of Arts about the perception of light, color, shape, and other physical concepts we see. Demonstration of seeing aspects of natural, scientific, and artistic elements. An ACI Release.
  - At the Time of Whaling, Sound, Color, 40 minutes. (Reel AV 1908)
    Film produced by and about the small Eskimo village of Gambell, on St. Lawrence Island in Alaska. Includes footage of whale hunting, a village-wide activity, as well as singing and dancing, cooking, family relations, and other Eskimo traditions in their general village life. Copyright 1975, the Village of Gambell and Leonard Kemerling.
  - Award-Winning Innovations in State and Local Government, 1988; Sound, Color, 30 minutes (Reel AV 1432)
    Presentation of social welfare programs in Kentucky, San Diego, and other cities around the U.S. Funded by the Ford Foundation and other organizations, these initiatives provide housing, food, education, and healthcare for a range of displaced people in need.
  - The Arab World's Past and Future, 1958; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1905)
    One of 15 lectures in a series entitled "A Changing World in the Light of History". Given by Arnold J. Toynebee at Washington & Lee University, Lexington VA, 1958. Produced by James Sage for Encyclopedia Brittanica. Copyright 1958.
  - The Arab World's Past and Future (Part Two), 1958; Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 1416)
  - Balanced and Unbalanced Forces, 1957; Sound, Color, 30 minutes (Reel AV 1504)
    An educational short film produced by Encyclopedia Brittanica as part of their course in physics, filmed in Pittsburgh public schools. With Processor Harvey E. White, University of California. Copyright Encyclopedia Brittanica Films Inc.
  - Battling Brook, 1968 September 3-7; Sound, Black & white, 23 minutes. (Reel AV 2009, Reel AV 2010, Reel AV 2012)
    Shot during 1968 September 3-7, this film explores the first four days after summer vacation of children ages 8-11 years old learning in a nontraditional schooling environment in Leicestershire, England. Produced in cooperation with the Public Education program of the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1969, Henry Felt.
  - Behavior of Gases, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 15 minutes. (Reel AV 1421)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Dr. Albert V. Baez.
  - Benjamin E. Mays: A Great Georgian, 1974; Sound, Color, 40 minutes. (Reel AV 1976)
    Documentary film based on the autobiography "Born to Rebel" of Morehouse College president Benjamin E. Mays. Film includes interviews with Dr Martin Luther King Sr., Jimmy Carter, Coretta Scott King, Samuel DuBois Cook, Edward B. Williams and John Danforth. Produced with a grant from the Ford Foundation. Grant # 75-31. Copyright University of Georgia, 1974.
  - Benin Kingship Ritual, Sound, Color, 21 minutes. (Reel AV 1920)
    Demonstrations of political and religious rites of the Oba, or King of the Benin region of West Africa. Footage of the Igua Blessing, Odudna Masquerare, and the Ugie-Erha-Oba Festival, with explanatory narrative. Produced for the Benin Historical Research Scheme by F.E. Speed and R.E. Bradbury.
  - Blackman's Burden, Sound, Color, 55 minutes. (Reel AV 1889)
    Short film examining post-colonial issues in under-developed nations, as seen by third world residents and their wealthy neighbor nations. Discusses issues of education and access, agriculture and industry, international economics, and the basic struggles of people in need. Written and directed by Richard Broad. Thames Colour Production.
  - Brothers and Sisters in Concert, 1974; Sound, Color, 1 hour 29 minutes. (Reel AV 2013)
    A concert film shot in Chicago during a five day business and arts exposition sponsored by Operation PUSH (People United to Save Humanity) with performances by Marvin Gaye, The Staple Singers, The Temptations, The Chi-Lites, The Main Ingredient, The O’Jays, Isaac Hayes, Zulema, The Cannonball Adderly Quintet, The Push Mass Choir, Albertina Walker, Loretta Oliver, Rev. James Cleveland, Bill Withers, Curtis Mayfield, Sammy Davis, Jr., Roberta Flack, Quincy Jones, Gladys Knight and the Pips, Jerry Butler, Brenda Lee Eager, The Ramsey Lewis Trio, Nancy Wilson and the Jackson 5. Copyright 1974, PUSH Foundation.
  - California Vs. Green, Sound, Color, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1890)
    Reenactment of a court case to illustrate methods of communication and interrogation in a court room. Produced by Charles Lesson and Eric Saltzman, with support from the National Endowment for the Humanities.
  - Canadian Conference on Education, Sound, Black& white, 31 minutes. (Reel AV 1907)
    Demonstration of the Tan-Gau method of secondary language instruction, as presented to a a group of Canadian 5th grade students. A teacher from Toronto, Raymond Duplantie, uses the Tan-Gau method to introduce basic vocabulary. Lessons 1 and 2 are shown, based on the work on Dr. Tan-Gwan Leong and Dr. Robert Gauthier. Produced for the Canadian Conference on Education and the Ford Foundation, with the Metropolitan Educational Televisions Association. A CFTO Production.
  - Career Education, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 2007)
    A documentary film about career education to equip young people with ideas about entering the industrial or commercial occupational fields. With an introduction from S.P. Maryland, Jr. Assistant Secretary for Education, Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
  - Carnot Cycle and Kelvin Cycle, 1951; Sound, Black & white, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 1881)
    Film from the "Basic Physics Series" about light and heat reactions, to be used in the classroom. Produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1951, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Citizens Conference, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1811)
    Documentary about issues in the education system, as demonstrated by schools in Montgomery County, Maryland. Poor communication between staff and students, unequal rights, overly strict polices, etc. are discussed in interviews and montages. "The questions we have tried to raise, and the points of view expressed, mainly reflect the interests of the only group involved in this problem, whose voices won?t be heard, that of the students".
  - Challenge in Africa, 1978; Sound, Color, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1839)
    Film about the work of the International Committee of the Red Cross in Africa; efforts to provide food, housing, and healthcare for Africans throughout the continent affected by war, civil unrest, and lack of infrastructure. Footage of battlegrounds in Chad, medical camps in Botswana, Rhodesian refugees, interviews with doctors and nurses working in rural clinics, etc. Some graphic footage.
  - Changing Work, 1975; Sound, Color, 22 minutes. (Reel AV 1797)
    Documentary about six American auto workers who spend time in a Saab factory in Sweden to learn about different trends of workplace design and organization. Their program was organized by Cornell University, Industrial and Labor Relations, under a grant from the Ford Foundation. Directed and edited by Peter Goldmann. Produced by Bjorn Ericstam, Sandell. Film, with Executive Producer David Hancock. Copyright maintained by the Ford Foundation.
  - Collision of Hard Spheres, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 1424)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland, produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation.
  - Color, Sound, Color, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1873)
    Brief science film explaining the physics of color, presented by the American Federation of Arts. Produced by ACI, with funding from the Ford Foundation.
  - Command Post, 1955 February 27; Sound, Black & white, 22 minutes. (Reel AV 1808)
    Introduction to the US Air Force's plans during the Cold War. The Continental Air Defense Command is introduced during a visit to an underground military base on Long Island, codenamed "COBRA". Anti-Soviet defenses, aviation technology, and national emergency preparedness are discussed. Version is incomplete, film ends suddenly.
  - The Common Good: New York State Legislature in Action, Sound, Black & white, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 2018)
    A documentary about he inner workings of New York State's Legislature filmed in Albany, New York at the State Capitol based on an idea by Albert J. Abrams, secretary of the Senate. Narrated by Dave Garroway. Written and Directed by David Epstein.
  - The Common Good: Social Welfare and the American Future, 1990; Sound, Color, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2019)